HG G 21.2, ETH Zürich, Rämistrasse 101 8092 Zürich, Switzerland Personal webpage: https://anmaillard.github.io email: antoine.maillard@math.ethz.ch

ABOUT ME

I am a Hermann-Weyl Instructor at the Institute for Mathematical Research (FIM) and the Department of Mathematics at ETH Zürich, working in the group of Prof. Afonso Bandeira. I defended my PhD in 2021 at École Normale Supérieure (ENS) de Paris, and prepared it under the supervision of Profs. Florent Krzakala and Lenka Zdeborová.

My research is at the intersection of high-dimensional statistics, probability theory, statistical physics, information theory, optimisation, and random matrix theory.

EDUCATION

• PhD in theoretical physics

2018-2021

"Fundamental limits of high-dimensional estimation"

Advised by Prof. Florent Krzakala & Prof. Lenka Zdeborová.

École Normale Supérieure, Paris, France

• École Normale Supérieure graduate degree

2013-2018

Research-oriented Master's degree validating my studies at ENS.

École Normale Supérieure, Paris, France

• M.Sc. in Theoretical Physics

2014-2016

2013-2014

2011-2013

Ranked $1^{st}/140$, grade: 18.82/20.

École Normale Supérieure, Paris, France

Master 1 in Mathematics

2013-2015

Overall grade: 17.86/20.

École Normale Supérieure, Paris, France

• B.Sc. in Physics
Ranked 2nd/35, grade: 18.8/20.

École Normale Supérieure, Paris, France

• Classes Préparatoires MPSI-MP

Admitted at ENS by competitive exams ("concours").

Lycée Sainte Geneviève, Versailles, France

TEACHING AND MENTORING

• Mathematics of Data Science

Fall 2023

Teaching (50 %) of a master's course in mathematics, 3 hours/week, $\simeq 150$ students – ETH Zürich. Based on the book draft: https://people.math.ethz.ch/~abandeira/BandeiraSingerStrohmer-MDS-draft.pdf

• Mathematics of Signals, Networks and Learning

Spring 2023

Teaching (50 %) of a bachelor course in mathematics, 2 hours/week, \simeq 60 students – ETH Zürich. Lecture notes: https://anmaillard.github.io/teaching/msnl spring 2023.pdf

• Student supervision at ETH Zürich

2021 - Now

- Student seminar on Matrix Discrepancy (Spring 2022)
- Mentoring of Cheng Shi, PhD student from the University of Basel (Spring 2024).
- Theses supervision of 3 students (Bachelor & Master):
 - * Kevin Lucca, Master Thesis, 2023. Norms of Random Multilinear Forms.
 - * Michał Mikuta, Bachelor Thesis, 2023. Average-Case Tensor Discrepancy: A First Moment Prediction.
 - * Fabio Hehli, Bachelor Thesis, 2022. Parallel Tempering for Tensor PCA.

• Teaching Assistant at ENS Paris

- 2018 2021
- "Mathematics for Physicists", taught by Prof. Van Wijland at ENS in Fall 2019, 2 hours/week.
- Participation in the design of competitive exams ("concours") of ENS in 2020.

• Private lessons 2013 - 2020

From highschool to bachelor degree, in physics and mathematics.

AWARDS & FELLOWSHIPS

• Hermann-Weyl-Instructor fellowship

2021-2024

Postdoctoral fellowship of ETH's Institute for Mathematical Research (FIM).

• Prix de thèse Daniel Guinier

2022

French nationwide PhD prize of the Société Française de Physique.

• PhD scholarship "Jean-Pierre Aguilar"

2018-2021

Competitive PhD scholarship from Fondation CFM pour la recherche.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

• Hermann-Weyl Instructor

Oct 2021 - Now

Post-doctoral position at ETH Zürich.

• Visit to Prof. Afonso Bandeira at ETH Zürich

Feb-Apr 2020

 $Invitation\ in\ the\ Department\ of\ Mathematics.$

• The rough high-dimensional landscape problem

Winter 2019

Two-months program at Kavli Institute for Theoretical Physics, Santa Barbara.

• Research internship, NYU (Shanghai & NYC)

 $Feb\text{-}Jul\ 2018$ w. G. Ben Arous.

Energy landscape of inference models

• Research internship, École Normale Supérieure (Paris)

Statistical learning and inference

Sep 2017 - Feb 2018 w. F. Krzakala.

• Research internship, Capital Fund Management (Paris)

Sep 2016 - Feb 2017

Message-passing algorithms for optimisation of discrete trade systems

w. J-P. Bouchaud & F. Altarelli.

• Research internship, CERN (Geneva, Switzerland)

Quadrupole structures for transverse Landau damping in circular accelerators

Jun-Jul 2016 w. E. Métral.

• Research internship, CEA & Collège de France (Paris)

Jan-May 2016

Out-of-equilibrium computations in quantum impurity models by Monte-Carlo methods

w. O. Parcollet & A. Georges.

• Research internship, Perimeter Institute (Waterloo, Canada)

 $Feb ext{-}Jul\ 2015$

Islands of stability and recurrence times in Anti-de-Sitter spacetimes

w. S. Green & L. Lehner.

• Intensive arabic internship (Cairo, Egypt)

At the "Institut Français d'Égypte", in El Mounira..

Aug-Sep 2014

LANGUAGE SKILLS

French (Native), English (Fluent), Arabic (Conversational), German (Basic).

PROGRAMMING SKILLS

Python, C++, Mathematica, LateX

OTHER SERVICES & RESPONSABILITIES

- Organisation of the DACO seminar from Fall 2021 until Fall 2023: https://math.ethz.ch/news-and-events/events/research-seminars/daco-seminar.html
- Outstanding Reviewer award at ICLR 2021.
- Reviewer for conferences : CAMSAP, NeurIPS, ICLR, ICML.
- Reviewer for journals: Foundations of Computational Mathematics, JSAIT, J. Stat. Mech., J. Phys. A,
 Phys. Rev. X, Information & Inference, Phys. Rev. Letters, Transactions in Machine Learning Research,
 SIAM Journal on Mathematics of Data Science.

SELECTED COMMUNICATIONS

Slides or notes can usually be found on my website. The communications are grouped by topic, and invited talks are highlighted.

Disordered systems and the mathematics of data science:

- (Invited) ARGO seminar, INRIA Paris (February 2024).
- (Invited) Disordered systems group, King's College London (January 2024).

On the ellipsoid fitting of random points:

- (Invited) Department of Mathematics, University of Fribourg, Switzerland (January 2024).
- (Invited) Probability and Statistics seminar, McMaster University, Canada (December 2023).
- (Invited) SIERRA seminar, INRIA Paris (December 2023).
- (Invited) Machine Learning and Signal Processing seminar, École Normale Supérieure de Lyon (November 2023).
- (Invited) Séminaire Centre science des données, École Normale Supérieure, Paris (November 2023).
- (Invited) Harvard CMSA Probability Seminar, Harvard University, USA (November 2023).
- (Invited) Statistical physics and machine learning back together again, Cargèse, France (August 2023).

On large-rank matrix denoising and factorisation:

- (Invited) 21st INFORMS Applied Probability Society Conference, Nancy, France (June 2023).
- (Invited) 29th Nordic Conference in Mathematical Statistics, Gothenburg, Sweden (June 2023).

On the injectivity of ReLU networks:

- (Invited) High Dimensional Statistics and Random Matrices, Porquerolles, France (June 2023).
- (Invited) Workshop on Spin Glasses, Les Diablerets, Switzerland (September 2022).

On high-dimensional phase retrieval:

- (Invited) Matrices et Graphes Aléatoires, Institut Henri Poincaré, Paris (December 2022).
- Youth in High dimensions (poster), ICTP, Trieste (June 2022).
- (Invited) Rigorous Evidence for Information-Computation Trade-offs, Simons Institute for the Theory of Computing, Berkeley (September 2021).
- Mathematical and Scientific Machine Learning, EPFL, Lausanne (August 2021).
- (Invited) Random Matrix Theory and Networks, Max Planck Institute for the Physics of Complex Systems, Dresden (June 2021).
- (Invited) INRIA seminar "Mokaplan", INRIA, Paris (December 2020).
- Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) (poster), Online (December 2020).

- Les Houches summer school on Statistical Physics and Machine Learning, Les Houches, France (August 2020).
- (Invited) Youth in high dimensions, ICTP, Trieste (June 2020).

On the landscape complexity of generalised linear models:

- (Invited) Probability Seminar, university of Basel (October 2021).
- Mathematical and Scientific Machine Learning, Princeton, USA (July 2020).

On the spiked matrix model with generative priors:

- Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) (poster), Vancouver, Canada (December 2019).
- Science of Data Science (poster), ICTP, Trieste (October 2019).

On the committee machine:

- Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) (poster), Montreal, Canada (December 2018).
- Cargese Summer School (poster), Cargese, France (August 2018).
- Beg Rohu Summer School (poster), Quiberon, France (June 2018).

More general talks:

- "Fundamental limits of high dimensional estimation", Rencontre des Jeunes Physicien(ne)s Ceremony for Daniel Guinier PhD award, Collège de France, Paris (November 2022).
- "On replica symmetry breaking", Graduate seminar of probability, ETH Zürich (October 2022).
- "The Kac-Rice formula", KITP, Santa Barbara and ETH Zürich (February 2019 and December 2022).

List of publications

On the order of authors – In most of my publications, the authors are ranked by order of contribution. However, in some works, the order is instead alphabetical. Whenever this is the case, this is indicated clearly by a symbol (α) .

PREPRINTS

- [1] **A. Maillard** and D. Kunisky. "Fitting an ellipsoid to random points: predictions using the replica method". arXiv preprint arXiv:2310.01169 (Oct. 2023).
- (α) [2] A. S. Bandeira and A. Maillard. "Exact threshold for approximate ellipsoid fitting of random points". $arXiv\ preprint\ arXiv:2310.05787\ (Oct.\ 2023).$
- (α) [3] A. S. Bandeira, A. Maillard, S. Mendelson, and E. Paquette. "Fitting an ellipsoid to a quadratic number of random points". arXiv preprint arXiv:2307.01181 (July 2023).
 - [4] **A. Maillard**, A. S. Bandeira, D. Belius, I. Dokmanić, and S. Nakajima. "Injectivity of ReLU networks: perspectives from statistical physics". arXiv preprint arXiv:2302.14112 (Feb. 2023).

JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

- (α) [5] A. S. Bandeira, A. Maillard, R. Nickl, and S. Wang. "On free energy barriers in Gaussian priors and failure of cold start MCMC for high-dimensional unimodal distributions". Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society A 381.2247 (2023), p. 20220150.
 - [6] J. Dong, L. Valzania, A. Maillard, T.-a. Pham, S. Gigan, and M. Unser. "Phase retrieval: From computational imaging to machine learning: A tutorial". *IEEE Signal Processing Magazine* 40.1 (2023), pp. 45–57.
 - [7] A. Maillard, F. Krzakala, M. Mézard, and L. Zdeborová. "Perturbative construction of mean-field equations in extensive-rank matrix factorization and denoising". *Journal of Statistical Mechanics: Theory and Experiment* 2022.8 (2022), p. 083301.
- (α) [8] A. S. Bandeira, A. Maillard, and N. Zhivotovskiy. "A remark on Kashin's discrepancy argument and partial coloring in the Komlós conjecture". *Portugaliae Mathematica* 79.3 (2022), pp. 311–316.
 - [9] **A. Maillard**. "Large deviations of extreme eigenvalues of generalized sample covariance matrices". *Europhysics Letters* 133.2 (2021), p. 20005.
 - [10] B. Aubin, B. Loureiro, A. Maillard, F. Krzakala, and L. Zdeborová. "The Spiked Matrix Model With Generative Priors". *IEEE Transactions on Information Theory* 67.2 (2020), pp. 1156–1181.
 - [11] A. Maillard, L. Foini, A. L. Castellanos, F. Krzakala, M. Mézard, and L. Zdeborová. "High-temperature expansions and message passing algorithms". *Journal of Statistical Mechanics: Theory and Experiment* 2019.11 (2019), p. 113301.
 - [12] B. Aubin, A. Maillard, J. Barbier, F. Krzakala, N. Macris, and L. Zdeborová. "The committee machine: computational to statistical gaps in learning a two-layers neural network". *Journal of Statistical Mechanics: Theory and Experiment* 2019.12 (2019), p. 124023.
 - [13] C. Bertrand, O. Parcollet, **A. Maillard**, and X. Waintal. "Quantum Monte Carlo algorithm for out-of-equilibrium Green's functions at long times". *Physical Review B* 100.12 (2019), p. 125129.
 - [14] M. Schenk, X. Buffat, K. Li, and A. Maillard. "Vlasov description of the effects of nonlinear chromaticity on transverse coherent beam instabilities". *Physical Review Accelerators and Beams* 21.8 (2018), p. 084402.
 - [15] S. R. Green, A. Maillard, L. Lehner, and S. L. Liebling. "Islands of stability and recurrence times in AdS". *Physical review D* 92.8 (2015), p. 084001.

CONFERENCE PUBLICATIONS

- [16] A. Maillard, F. Krzakala, Y. M. Lu, and L. Zdeborová. "Construction of optimal spectral methods in phase retrieval". *Mathematical and Scientific Machine Learning*. PMLR. 2022, pp. 693–720.
- [17] E. Troiani, V. Erba, F. Krzakala, A. Maillard, and L. Zdeborová. "Optimal denoising of rotationally invariant rectangular matrices". *Mathematical and Scientific Machine Learning*. PMLR. 2022, pp. 97–112.
- [18] **A. Maillard**, G. Ben Arous, and G. Biroli. "Landscape complexity for the empirical risk of generalized linear models". *Mathematical and Scientific Machine Learning*. PMLR. 2020, pp. 287–327.
- [19] **A. Maillard**, B. Loureiro, F. Krzakala, and L. Zdeborová. "Phase retrieval in high dimensions: Statistical and computational phase transitions". *Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems* 33 (2020), pp. 11071–11082.
- [20] B. Aubin, B. Loureiro, A. Maillard, F. Krzakala, and L. Zdeborová. "The spiked matrix model with generative priors". Proceedings of the 33rd International Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems. 2019, pp. 8366–8377.
- [21] B. Aubin, A. Maillard, F. Krzakala, N. Macris, L. Zdeborová, et al. "The committee machine: Computational to statistical gaps in learning a two-layers neural network". *Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems* 31 (2018).
- [22] J. Barbier, N. Macris, **A. Maillard**, and F. Krzakala. "The mutual information in random linear estimation beyond iid matrices". 2018 IEEE International Symposium on Information Theory (ISIT). IEEE. 2018, pp. 1390–1394.

PhD thesis

[23] A. Maillard. "Fundamental limits of high-dimensional estimation: a stroll between statistical physics, probability and random matrix theory". PhD thesis. Université Paris sciences et lettres, 2021.

LECTURE NOTES

- [24] A. S. Bandeira and A. Maillard. Mathematics of Signals, Networks, and Learning. 2023. URL: https://anmaillard.github.io/teaching/msnl spring 2023.pdf.
- [25] **A. Maillard**. The Kac-Rice formula: basic definitions and a first application. 2019. URL: https://anmaillard.github.io/teaching/kac_rice_2019.pdf.